tremendous crash of glass.
No one stirred in the farmhouse before noon on the following day,
and the word went round that from somewhere or other the pigs had acquired
the money to buy themselves another case of whiskey.
Chapter 10.
Years passed. The seasons came and went.
The short animal lives fled by.
A time came when there was no one who remembered the old days before the rebellion,
except Clover, Benjamin, Moses the Raven, and a number of the pigs.
Muriel was dead.
Bluebell, Jessie, and Pincher were dead.
Jones, too, was dead. He had died in an inebriates' home in another part of the county.
Snowball was forgotten.
Boxer was forgotten, except by the few who had known him.
Clover was an old stout mare now, stiff in the joints and with a tendency to rheumy eyes.
She was 2 years past the retiring age, but in fact, no animal had ever actually retired.
The talk of setting aside a corner of the pasture for superannuated animals
had long since been dropped.
Napoleon was now a mature boar of 24 stone.
Squealer was so fat that he could, with difficulty, see out of his eyes.
Only old Benjamin was much the same as ever, except for being a little grayer about the muzzle,
and, since Boxer's death, more morose and taciturn than ever.
There were many more creatures on the farm now, though the increase was not so great as
had been expected in earlier years.
Many animals had been born to him the rebellion was only a dim tradition
passed on by word of mouth, and others had been bought who had never heard
mention of such a thing before their arrival.
The farm possessed three horses now besides Clover.
They were fine, upstanding beasts, willing workers, and good comrades, but very stupid.
None of them proved able to learn the alphabet beyond the letter B.
They accepted everything that they were told about the rebellion and the
principles of animalism, especially from Clover, for whom they had an almost filial respect,
but it was doubtful whether they understood very much of it.
The farm was more prosperous now and better organized.
It had even been enlarged by two fields, which had been bought from Mr.
Pilkington.
The windmill had been successfully completed at last, and the farm possessed a threshing
machine and a hay elevator of its own, and various new buildings had been added to it.
Whymper had bought himself a dog cart.
The windmill, however, had not, after all, been used for generating electrical power.
It was used for milling corn and brought in a handsome money profit.
The animals were hard at work building yet another windmill.
When that one was finished, so it was said, the dynamos would be installed.
But the luxuries of which Snowball had once taught the animals to dream,
the stalls with electric light and hot and cold water, and the three-day week,
were no longer talked about.
Napoleon had denounced such ideas as contrary to the spirit of animalism.
"The truest happiness," he said, "lay in working hard and living frugally."
Somehow it seemed as though the farm had grown richer without making the animals
themselves any richer, except of course for the pigs and the dogs.
Perhaps this was partly because there were so many pigs and so many dogs.
It was not that these creatures did not work after their fashion.
There was, as Squealer was never tired of explaining, endless work in the
supervision and organization of the farm.
Much of this work was of a kind that the other animals were too ignorant to understand.
For example, Squealer told them that the pigs had to expend enormous labors every
day upon mysterious things called files, reports, minutes, and memoranda.
These were large sheets of paper which had to be closely covered with writing,
and as soon as they were so covered, they were burnt in the furnace.
"This was of the highest importance for the welfare of the farm," Squealer said,
"but still neither pigs nor dogs produced any food by their own labor,
and there were very many of them, and their appetites were always good."
As for the others, their life, so far as they knew, was as it had always been.
They were generally hungry. They slept on straw.
They drank from the pool.
They labored in the fields.
In winter, they were troubled by the cold, and in summer by the flies.
Sometimes the older ones among them racked their dim memories and tried to
determine whether in the early days of the rebellion, when Jones's expulsion
was still recent, things had been better or worse than now.
They could not remember.
There was nothing with which they could compare their present lives.
They had nothing to go upon except Squealer's lists of figures,
which invariably demonstrated that everything was getting better and better.
The animals found the problem insoluble.
In any case, they had little time for speculating on such things now.
Only old Benjamin professed to remember every detail of his long life
and to know that things never had been nor ever could be much better or much worse.
Hunger, hardship, and disappointment being, so he said, the unalterable law of life.
And yet, the animals never gave up hope.
More, they never lost, even for an instant, their sense of honor and privilege in
being members of Animal Farm.
They were still the only farm in the whole country, in all England,
owned and operated by animals.
Not one of them, not even the youngest, not even the newcomers who had been
brought from farms 10 or 20 miles away, ever ceased to marvel at that.
And when they heard the gun booming and saw the green flag fluttering at the
masthead, their hearts swelled with imperishable pride.
And the talk turned always towards the old heroic days, the expulsion of Jones,
the writing of the Seven Commandments, the great battles in which the human
invaders had been defeated.
None of the old dreams had been abandoned.
The Republic of the animals, which Major had foretold when the green fields of
England should be untrodden by human feet was still believed in.
Someday it was coming.
It might not be soon.
It might not be within the lifetime of any animal now living, but still it was coming.
Even the tune of Beasts of England was perhaps hummed secretly here and there.
At any rate, it was a fact that every animal on the farm knew it, though no
one would have dared to sing it aloud.
It might be that their lives were hard and that not all of their hopes had been fulfilled,
but they were conscious that they were not as other animals.
If they went hungry, it was not from feeding tyrannical human beings.